[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
keeping your teams on top of the latest
tech developments is a monumental
challenge
helping them get answers to urgent
problems they face daily is even harder
that's why 66 percent of all fortune 100
companies count on o'reilly online
learning
at o'reilly your teams will get live
courses tons of resources
interactive scenarios and sandboxes and
fast answers to their pressing questions
see what o'reilly online learning can do
for your teams
visit o'reilly.com for a demo
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host gavin henry and today my
guest is jamie riedesol
jamie reed essel is a staff engineer at
dropbox
working on their hello sign product she
has over 20 years of experience in the
technical field
starting with office i t moving to
systems
administration and engineering and most
recently in devops
she has been presenting at technical
conferences since 2015
on topics such as log stash optimization
monitoring system refactoring
and how to get over your workplace
introduced traumas
jamie welcome to software engineering
radio is there anything i missed in your
bio that you'd like to add
those are the major points thank you
excellent
i'd like to start first of all with an
overview of what software telemetry is
its terms and its history so jamie what
is
software telemetry at its broadest level
software telemetry is what we all use to
figure out what our software is
actually doing quite frankly i mean when
you're writing software
what is how is it that you find out that
it's doing what it should
and that's only a little rhetorical
because if it's working exactly the way
it should
great but if it doesn't software
telemetry tells you why
it's those little print statements we
scatter all over our code
to give us feedback on what's going on
it's us instrumenting this black box
that we're writing
to tell us how it's working and i mean
that
that's software telemetry at its
broadest level
and frankly it's we've been doing it for
decades and decades at the donna
computing software telemetry was an
indicator light on the computer showing
a little processing whether it was
blinking fast or slow
told you if it was doing it the right
job at the right speed
later on we got into paper you know it
actually print out things or pop
something up on an operator console when
something went wrong
and these days we now have robust
systems
centralized logging that's been around
for a long time probably the first major
software telemetry system but we've also
added on metrics
it's kind of an extension of the old
operations monitoring concept but
tracing has been added on there
and it's all been rounded up in the last
few years into the concept of the
pillars of observability which is all
about making your systems observable
so software telemetry are the components
of your observable systems
thank you and if we could sort of boil
that down to one sentence
why do we need software telemetry
software telemetry tells you what's
going on in the black box we're building
okay and how is it used once we know
what's going on in the black box we're
building
oh every individual developer does it a
little differently
but that's one of those fun concepts
because when you're
writing software on your own on your own
box on your own stuff all by yourself
you can do whatever you want by yourself
however it is you need to know what's
going on in there that's creating
log files or maybe you have a different
stream
a little pop-up on your website that a
little bug that pops up that gives you
rendering times
for things all these little things are
software telemetry and but thing is that
very
large systems or anytime you get more
than one developer involved or if you've
or probably a better way to put it is if
like a small team is more likely to use
something like a software as a service
platform or new relic or
data dog or honeycomb type systems to be
able to
figure out what's going on in there kind
of across the team
and use software telemetry a little bit
differently
in a small team and when you get to the
truly big ones you're talking those
global data centers where you have
software that gets deployed to data
center after data center as part of your
canary process you know the google size
software
so let me try that scale is very
different than it is down at when it's
just
five people working on a thing kind of
as a hobby and but the thing is it's all
the same thing in the end it's just
what we want to learn about our code is
the same but just how you approach it
differs a little bit based on how many
people you have to coordinate
the engineering discipline you're all
following the languages you're using
because not everything is
fully instrumented for things so when
we're thinking of
the general term software telemetry what
the key terms we should keep
in our head when we start moving into
the next sections of the
show for example things like cardinality
oh yes there's like four major types of
telemetry that i talk about
centralized logging which is all your
logs outputs the events little
text-based snippets of saying what
happened when
your metrics are all numbers based
they'll have generally a few little data
tags to give you an idea as to where it
was when this thing was it was issued
like
number of pages converted or bytes
uploaded that sort of thing
and the traces are more of your
distributed tracing concept
where you have follows execution and it
traces timing and some context right
there
also i do cover a seam system the
security event information management
system
this is what security teams use and it
gets a little underappreciated when it
comes to telemetry simply because
people forget the security team is there
but it's also a kind of extension of
centralized logging so those are the
four
styles of telemetry that i talk about
but there's others
cardinality is a major concept when it
comes to
maintaining telemetry systems especially
the data stores behind them
because cardinality is one of the key
constraints in the databases we use for
this
and which database you use for your
centralized logging system is usually
different than the one you use for your
time series databases
which is your metric systems and how
those two systems respond to cardinality
is very different but
cardinality also means different things
at different databases we can talk a bit
about that if you want to i can have an
entire chapter on that
you've done a nice intro to the next
section i'll move us on to
shortly but if i could ask at the high
level
because we'll dig deep into other topics
shortly
how is software telemetry different from
analytics or logging or monitoring
the thing is it's all really the same
thing just it's just a label i used for
that that's what i thought
i just thought i cleared up yeah
monitoring is uh honestly monitoring is
where i first ran into software
telemetry
like early in my career i came from the
operations system inside and we called
metrics monitoring you know
i mean i've given talks and how to
improve your monitoring system
and how to only alarm on the right
things i mean that's all
that's a metric system being used in a
specific way
but honestly metrics is an extension
and a lot of ways of monitoring but
because the software engineering team
said to the operations teams like you
got this cool system can we get in on
that
and we started seeing these conversions
of purpose
but analytics is also another way of
describing
these concepts it's a form of metrics
it's also a part of tracing as well
you also see application performance
management thrown around a lot
that is another concept that kind of
merges some of the metrics and tracing
concepts in a lot of ways but it's still
software telemetry
so would you say software telemetry is
like the foundation term and then it
gets scooped up in analytics or logging
or monitoring based on what
telemetry data is coming in is that a
good way to think about it that is a
good way to think about it yes
the word the term telemetry for this is
fairly new quite frankly
the most interesting product project
going on right now in the telemetry
space
is the open telemetry project from the
cloud native computing foundation which
is
trying to build a transmission protocol
for traces
for the distributed tracing product and
they have this idea
that they can extend it to do things
like logging and metrics along the same
protocol once they get done with it it's
still being built right now we'll see
what they actually come out with
but telemetry seems to be a new term
that's encompassing a lot of these
older been around for ages type of terms
this industry likes to eat it's dead and
this is one way it's doing it
i like that term yeah i suppose they're
moving towards
trying to standardize something aren't
they oh sure yeah
it helps just briefly on this one
because i know
we've both got a passion for this
subject so we could talk a lot longer
than an hour
how did it evolve in relation to
developments and networking hardware
to where we are today you know because
you've got a lovely chapter in your book
which we haven't mentioned yet
which is called software telemetry
published by manning
how did we get to where we are today
with developments of the underlying
network and hardware do you think well
this
is a fun story because software
telemetry
the developer feedback side of it took a
while to emerge i mean we first started
seeing some signs of it
in the early 1970s but that was a very
limited era of computing
printers were probably our biggest
biggest avenue for that but at the same
time you're also getting a bit more
display technologies advancing
what i think of is that one of the key
turning points for software telemetry
and telemetry usage in general
was the syslog product which came out of
send mail the three bsd thing around
1980 i can't find the exact genealogy of
when it started but syslog
came out of the send mail project and
other systems just said hey we've got
this logger here why can't we just use
that so peop
other projects sort of picked it up and
started sending things to this
email logger which at the time was one
of the biggest log producing
pieces of software on on various systems
you know the email handler
so that was where we sat for a long time
and
syslog moved forward until we got to
about 2001
2002 somewhere in there when a group of
people decided to standardize this thing
because it hadn't been standardized yet
so they created a group of rfcs to
standardize the syslog protocol
standards are good things because it
means it's stable so you know
what it is and how it works and that
gave so many things
an ability to predict how to emit things
now rewinding the clock a little bit we
have to look at the parallel evolution
of network
stuff those of you who have been in the
networking world know that
a lot of it ran on we were running on
serial before running on ethernet or
anything else i mean the
networking of the 1970s and earlier was
all rs232
very serial and the networking equipment
that came in in the 80s 90s and early
2000s
all used serial connections to configure
but at the same time
they also started working with
network-based
methods of communicating and most
networking hardware used something
called the simple network management
protocol
a udp-based thing to talk with the
centralized systems for configuration
and reporting events you know
telemetry system quite frankly so that
was the networking's
parallel evolution now fast forward kind
of more in 2010s and we're finally
seeing some real conversions between the
software space and the hardware space
so this law continued to be used on the
software side but a lot of
hardware makers realize hey this is a
standard we can actually safely use so
over the first decade of this century
we saw a lot of hardware makers start
adding in syslog support to their
systems
to just ease integration with the rest
of the infrastructure people are running
meanwhile we had software doing its own
dang thing
and kind of rewind back to the 90s a
centralized logging was the
first real telemetry system we had and
back in those days it was
you had a few servers they spat out
syslog files and you copied the syslog
files across an nfs
share to a shared directory that you
then use tools like grep to go looking
for whatever it is you're looking for
you know it was very simple back in
those days not much in the way of
databases although a few did actually do
things like
fork their their web logs into
relational databases
and that model lasted for a while and
that gave people
that gave rise to sophisticated
dashboards that we would recognize quite
frankly as
analytics and analyzing traffic flow
and raising the view of errors i mean
this
very focused type of telemetry in those
days was
powerful and it kind of proved what
would come later
fast forward again to about 2010 and we
started seeing the convergence of
the old monitoring systems into the
metric systems
and we started seeing products like etsy
released statsd which is
a small daemon udp based that could take
statistics
information coming from software and a
fire hose and just send that into
whatever your your back end was and that
was variable and actually
a good point for the product so we
started seeing
the metrics there but at the same time
the hardware stuff is still emitting in
these centralized logging systems
and that monitoring systems operate
operating teams are using we're also
still monitoring the network hardware
you know how much traffic are you doing
on a given network port i mean that's
still a form of metrics it's just
not what software engineers usually
think of as metrics that's you know
monitoring so these days in the modern
infrastructure
here we are at 2021 you've got
a converged infrastructure in a lot of
ways you know the networking team may
have their own
but you have the possibility of a single
interface
probably grafana these days that can get
you network port information
it could also give you logs it can also
give you
execution rates for given functions in a
given data center or given rack you can
split things down that far it's come a
long ways
and one of the most interesting
evolutions i've seen
was around probably 2015 it's a big
inflection point
is when distributed tracing really
started getting a lot of
mind share in a lot of ways because this
was the idea of using high cardinality
metrics to be able to trace execution
across a distributed infrastructure
which is a problem that microservices
infrastructures had because
you got 50 to 100 different services
doing their own thing how do you follow
execution across all that and that's
how that was solved confusingly those
early systems were called observability
systems but we've since dropped that
term in favor of the
pillars of observability so yeah there's
been a lot of a lot of movement and
quite frankly over the next 10 years i
fully expect something new to come along
that i haven't seen
so my goal is to get people thinking
about the generalities
so when the new stuff shows up you're
able to work with it effectively and
implement it thank you jimmy that was a
great history lesson
you do really know your stuff thank you
we've done a previous show episode 220
with john gifford i think on logging and
logging infrastructure which is a good
listen
and episode 337 for the listeners ben
siegelman on distributed tracing and
i'll put some others in the show notes
so just before i move us on to some of
the topics you've already mentioned i
think you might have answered this one
already
what does the simplest form of telemetry
look like
i think i can guess the answer you're
probably not wrong it's a simple log
file
i mean it's it's easiest every
programming language i know of has some
way to send text
into a file and then the telemetry bit
would be getting that
remote file to somewhere central or is
that just
after the fact it depends you know if
it's a truly a single system box you
know your your telemetry may be simply
just
looking at the file whatever tools you
have available but if you get a
multi-machine infrastructure
then you want to start centralizing it
that gets some more interesting
infrastructures
what's the most complex you've seen
complex yes
i've heard of some very interesting
complex
ones complex comes up when you get these
sort of global spanning sas
products where you do follow the sun
deploys and your canary
deploys involve millions of users
because a million is actually small for
you
in those circumstances the telemetry
systems tend to be very full of
aggregation summarization and just
sampling simply because you can't
catch the entire flood of it all so
in these situations you get data centers
have their own pools of high
resolution telemetry they get summarized
up the tree into kind of a higher
regional or maybe global level tiers
where you've
for the grand highest the apex thing
that builds the dashboards on the wall
the headquarters
are showing you highly summarized
information for how everything's working
those systems are incredibly complex and
those type of systems are the kind you
get when you have an
entire department of engineers whose job
it is to make this stuff
work and you don't see those very often
unless you see those at the biggest
companies
perfect you can only keep those for so
long as well so it depends on
your time history right perfect let's
move us on to the next section
so we're going to talk about the types
of software telemetry which you've
touched on
we'll drill down into some system
components
and we'll round off the show with
talking about telemetry data
in resource-constrained personal
environments
so now that we've covered off the basics
in history i'd like to explore the main
types of telemetry discussed in your
book
which is called software telemetry
published by manning which i've already
mentioned
the first point i've got is centralized
logging
can you give me an example of that
please centralized logging
probably the most famous example people
have heard of before is the elk stack
which is the elastic search logstash and
kibana
that elastic.co has been is made famous
over the course of the 2010s
it wasn't all elastic at first logstash
and cabana both are outside projects
that were later acquired
but that is the idea is you have all of
your logs
flowing to a central place that you have
a graphical ui of some kind
to be able to search create dashboards
and bisect resect whatever you need to
do to figure
out just dive into that information and
the value of centralized logging is that
presentation it's all in one place
you can search all of it there and that
gives you the best chance to be able to
learn something
from your pile of logs the the old
school method of just putting a bunch of
files on a
on a nfs share somewhere that you had to
manually cut through with
text-based tools maybe more purely unix
but it's a terrible user experience and
most people generally didn't bother
thank you and
and of course they've uh caused a bit of
upheaval with their license chains
this year oh that's a whole thing yes it
is
we won't talk about that but yeah so the
next one would be
the term metrics if you give me an
example of that please
metrics really is all about sending
numbers
it is the law kind of in the evolution
of telemetry
centralized logging was the first one
it's all text based metrics is the next
one is people realize that if you can
just kind of reduce your telemetry down
to numbers numbers store very
conveniently
and compactly and you can store a lot
more of it online as
had been proven by the monitoring
systems operations i've been using
where with centralized logging you
rarely get more in a month or two online
with metrics because of how they
compress
better summarize you can get whole years
of this stuff and once you have that
kind of long
baseline you can learn so many things
about your how your production systems
operates and other things so yeah
metric systems are all about that so
that would be more like
how quickly something's happened how
long how
many things have been used load all that
type of stuff that's particular to your
application or
yep sector counters and timers are the
two most popular
types how often a thing happens and how
long did it take
i think you've mentioned observe
observability a few times but
what is this observability observability
is an umbrella term
for logs metrics and traces and it's
been
an interesting ride just because like i
mentioned in 2015 16 or thereabouts it
was actually banging about as a separate
telemetry style but people realize
no actually observability is kind of a
methodology rather than a specific
style of telemetry it's about
integrating these three pillars the logs
the metrics the traces into something
that can work together reinforce each
other
to give you the most visibility in what
your production systems are doing
did that come out of the market
marketing department or the engineering
department
that's a little bit of the marketing i
believe
honeycomb io is probably the most famous
vendor in the observability space
they probably are the first to try to
market on the term but
the word itself has been gone and more
of a discipline as opposed to a
specific style i suppose like devops or
something you know
kinda yeah yeah as someone who has
devops in her job title
that is something that has a lot of
opinions behind it
cool i think you mentioned this as well
distributed tracing
could you give me an example of that and
i've also got
my notes here the open tracing project
open tracing dot io yeah open tracing
open telemetry is the more
is kind of the successor to that one i
believe but the idea behind distributed
tracing is to again
embrace the graph power of gooeys
when you're when you're writing a
program you open
so when you enter a function and one of
the things you do if you're using a
tracing system is you kind of
use the sdk to mark okay this i'm going
to trace this pot
you do some work and then you close the
trace and it reports it on the back end
you just instrument your code this way
and sort of trust in the
open trace the distributed tracing
automation to help you so on the other
end of that when you're looking back to
see what happened when
all that code markup you've done and the
traces that come out of that can be re
you can use that to reassemble what is
functionally a stack
trace for your distributed system where
each function was waiting for output
you have what called in there it's a
complete call stack
and if that happens to be involved
systems that run different
platforms or even different continents
you can still have it assembled on the
same
interface which gives you so much
intuitive power
when you're looking at it because it
surfaces so many things an example i use
is like if an upstream process has a
fault but it can still
reports code a downstream process can
return an exception on that one with the
centralized logging system you just see
the exception but none of the context
that came before it
in a distributed tracing system you'd be
able to look at that interface and see
that there's a previous system
through some weird stuff and it's very
visible and you can look at that earlier
execution and see what it did very
quickly whereas with the centralized
logging system you'd have to have some
fluency with a centralized logging
system to be able to know
how execution usually flows and kind of
walk back the execution to where those
logs are kept
whereas it's distributed tracing it
surfaces those weirdnesses far easier
what did you mean by it's still
producing code
you're instrumenting code all right okay
yeah it's still spitting out something
so your distributed tracing you could if
i imagined it like a google maps
you could have a high level view that
might be the interactions between
microservices or functions as a service
for example and then you could maybe
zoom in
and get the tracing within the same
function or
series of method calls or you know
classes is that the sort of thing that's
possible
yeah that is it's very powerful stuff
but if you haven't used it before it can
really blow your mind when you're
finally seeing it working on a product
that you know it's like wow this is all
put together in one spot you know the
system i
i use at work we have a lot of the
basics for
for some of the distributed tracing
concepts but we don't have it wired
together quite yet
but thing is is that you can get the
same kind of detail from centralized
logging you just have to be far more
fluent in what your logging looks like
and what your
how your operational flow is to be able
to get that sort of detail
distributed tracing when done correctly
means someone
needs far less training and prior
history and intuition to be able to find
the good stuff it's powerful stuff i was
thinking
with your example for centralized
logging there i had a
situation where an error appeared in the
central logging which happened to be an
elk stack and there was a clear error i
couldn't
basically say i couldn't do this because
i put the together the system i knew
what
what happened before that but if one of
my colleagues were looking at a
distributed tracing system
would be perfect because then you can
actually see what it was trying to do
before that
you know what time of day it was and all
all those different stages
so i totally get your example there
thanks right the last one in this
section would be what you've mentioned
already
same or seem security information event
management
could you explain that and give me an
example please this is one that's kind
of a black box to most software
engineers because they don't work with
it quite frankly uh this is a
specialized form of centralized logging
no software engineers uh think of
security
yeah i know some security people have
tried to do software but
the thing is is that these systems are
kind of very specialized for the
security mission
and that falls directly out of
regulatory frameworks
that require certain level of
sophistication for your ability to trace
who did what when what did they do when
did they do that and how did they do it
you need to be able to
for these regulatory frameworks
construct what an operator did
they logged into this system they used
sudo to do these five commands
or someone logged into an admin portal
they did these nine things
of which four of which did and be able
to build those traces
same systems are functionally very
similar to centralized logging but the
thing is is that they're also using
very tightly focused telemetry signals
these are like audit logs coming out of
your windows and linux systems
these are command logs coming out of
your
software as a service providers they
provide an audit log such as that
and they're all unified together in a
way that allows security people to
trace what happened use this to set
alarms for things that happened
an example for us is that if someone
logs into the root account of our amazon
account
security gets told that has a seam
function and that's because
logging into the root account is
something we don't do routinely
so every time it happens someone needs
to be told just in case someone's going
to do some bad stuff
so seam systems are kind of like
centralized logging but the thing is is
that
they're because of the security function
they need to keep out online
way longer so they have to be highly
selective in what they put in there
perfect and i suppose that depends on
again the sector the product the
distributed tracing
is that log instantly shipped across the
network or saved locally or you know
so there's a lot to think about there
isn't there quite a lot yeah
and that that leads to some very
interesting discussions you can have
internally when you're looking at this
stuff because
different sectors of the industry
sectors have different
integrity requirements for their tracing
or their events and their telemetry
and you can definitely do things like
create an
end-to-end digitally signed telemetry
flow you can do that you have high
integrity
you know something's been tampered with
pretty much immediately because you
stopped getting choices
you can do that but the trade-off there
is fragility and
that's a quite that's a business risk
that each organization needs to make for
themselves
and somebody different markets have
different different requirements quite
frankly finance and healthcare
have very strict requirements where
selling lawn mowers perhaps maybe
isn't as strict at o'reilly
we know your tech teams need quick
answers to their most urgent questions
they need to stay on top of new tech
developments they need a safe place to
learn the technologies your company
adopts
and they need it all 24 7. well they can
get it all
at o'reilly.com with o'reilly online
learning your team gets live online
courses
tons of resources safe interactive
scenarios and sandboxes
and fast answers to their most pressing
questions
visit o'reilly.com and request a demo
so i'd like to talk about example
telemetry system components now
and discuss breaking down a complete
telemetry system
what's the best way to do this actually
should we pick a sector that's really
quite simple to break apart or should we
pick a
web app for example that's probably
easiest uh web app is probably
uh probably the most easiest for people
and i can kind of walk you through
the growth pattern from like small to
global if we need to that's perfect
so if we take a web application so a
front end and a browser
database on a couple of virtual machines
shall we say
what would the key components of a
telemetry system be
in relation to that for something like
for like an
early small system you got like maybe
five people working on it quite frankly
at that stage almost all of it's going
to be software as a service
so just pick something online and go for
it kind of yeah your javascript
application is
probably going to some place like sentry
and if you're your backend code maybe go
into new rolex or datadog or something
like that
and you're not going to be spending any
time building telemetry products you'd
be marking up your code for that
but you're not going to be doing things
like picking data stores and
figuring out how to transform it along
the way or just not big enough yet
that stuff happens when you get more
talent and when the engineering
organization gets big enough
that you have the skill to be able to
maintain your own internal stuff
at that scale how do we choose what to
store
and what to ship at the smaller scale
probably the biggest constraint is cost
each software
as a service vendor i know of sets their
pricing based on
ingestion rate of some way size in some
cases
so a lot of ways is let's put it a
different way
engineers will instrument literally
every line of code if they can get away
with it just so they can fully trace it
get that sort of virtual debugging
experience
you know set debug mode and try to step
through the code one line at a time if
you need to
that is the worst case when you don't
trust your code one bit
but the best case is you get a single
event when everything goes completely
and you're all done but
every environment somewhere in between
figuring out what to send has to do with
balancing the costs of ingestion versus
the
cost to your application for actually
emitting that stuff because every time
you emit an event or a telemetry it's a
little bit of
parasitic load away from your production
application so it's a big balancing act
so yeah my next question was are these
the same
but i guess if you're using a software
as a server system
the things that you ship could be the
most things important that you need to
find quickly
urgently and the things that you store
could be more longer term
is that a good way to think of that
possibly yes the software is a service
provider method
is like you'd send real-time events to
them because you want to
you're probably building dashboards
somewhere you may even have alarm setup
but for longer term that would be
throwing a bunch of events into
something like an s3 bucket we're just
sort of throwing it to the future and
trust that your future people know how
to purse this stuff
and if you need to dig through it
someone may have some scripts to bisect
and reset and reassemble if you need to
but it's very much an ad hoc thing for
that that cold storage is
not built out at the smaller stage and
when you get to sort of the medium and
larger stage your engineering org is
bigger you probably have some more
devops risk re-type people around and
that means you may be able to handle
self-hosting some of this stuff
you know work about work and if you will
and that point yeah
that then you can start having the
discussions of do we want to inboard
stuff from the software as a service
systems because we figure we can
maintain it better or easier cheaper for
whatever reason
that threshold is different for every
organization some places stay with
software as a service as a strategic
move all the way up to global dominance
stage
the kind where when the sales
representatives are in town they take
you out to dinner every time because you
are such good customers
yeah i i guess that's a business
decision doesn't it oh yeah i absolutely
would be at that size
in this example um of the web
application where should telemetry data
get emitted from and save to
if we're using sas we just save it on
the service but where should we
yeah for sas for the like for the
smaller medium sized
web application it's almost always going
to be some sort of web api of some kind
because that's kind of the native
language of web applications is http
apis
and the sas vendors have ways to do that
you just ship it through there
it gets interesting when you get into
these like restricted environments like
governmental stuff where you can
have to work everything through a proxy
and you can't talk directly to the
internet
that gets some fun you get some fun
engineering when you get those sorts of
circumstances
should it be shipped real time or in
batch or
was that a decision you need to make
that's a decision you need to make but
keep in mind that the longer telemetry
is on whatever produced it
that state you're keeping and that state
can be modified by an attacker
so if you're trying to build defensible
telemetry versus an attacker you want to
move telemetry as fast as possible
off of whatever produced it so that is a
design goal you should be aiming towards
is to evacuate that stuff
as often much as you can like if you're
in containers or functions as a service
you can't trust that local state anyway
so you got to evacuate it just because
of your development model
but if you're on actual servers you
still want to do this because if an
attacker gets on the box the first thing
they're going to try to do is try to
modify the traces that show they were
there
okay and should this be always on which
i think you've just said or should we
trigger it on demand
very much always on i know some
organizations try to
if especially if they're on actual
servers like have a once an hour cron
job or a
windows task manager job just a copy log
someplace else
and then they're batch ingested at that
point you
actually see this model more often in
companies that have things like
branch offices or retail or they have
like a computer closet somewhere
before they all went online anyway you'd
get these sort of hourly or
months a day batch uploads of telemetry
from these areas into the central board
and it processed at that point but with
networking the way it is these days
you're seeing that model less and less
yeah i mean you just know something's
going to happen before the date is
shipped oh yeah you can't do anything
about it
so what happens if it all stops working
do we care
do we need to monitor our telemetry you
very much do
i have found as someone who manages this
stuff when the logs stop
flowing i get called and slack hey logs
aren't showing up is something wrong
i mean people will come at you as soon
as they can because software engineers
love that feedback of what's going on in
production
they're responding to bugs coming from
supports and to do that they have to
research
your telemetry systems all three kinds
and if they're not there their job is
stopped and that's a blocking workflow
you need to fix it so yeah
you definitely do this is a system you
do need to maintain availability for
so if you're doing service level
agreements and service level objectives
your telemetry systems need to be are
subjected to that just as well because a
large number of your organization
rely on this to do their job effectively
and if it's gone
they you get the word we're blocked
we're blocked we're blocked all over the
place and no one likes
blocking especially in agile
organizations and do you ever find
yourself
just going back to these guys are you
actually using the logs now
why do i need to be bothered you know
there is that temptation but
uh i've i've also been myself using them
because the thing is about
okay here's one of the secrets about ops
type roles is that we're kind of the
backstop
i need some help troubleshooting
something so we get tagged into a lot of
weird and different things and if we
stick around for a while and i've been
at this job for just over five years so
i've seen some weird things
we just sort of build that intuition
about what normal looks like and what
abnormal looks like in the various ways
that things
fail so yeah i've been in those systems
too and if they're not there i feel cut
off as well so yeah
they're critical systems that we keep up
and we need to have reliability
guarantees too
simply because they are they're decision
support systems
these telemetry systems at their core
are what people who maintain software
systems use to determine if they're
doing the right job
yeah it's i suppose it's like driving a
car without any dashboard
you know you you need that constant
feedback at this scale
what open source tools do you recommend
that someone could get start with
started with to get this data into the
sas providers
the thing is is that every sas provider
provides an sdk of some kind for the
various languages
i reckon definitely recommend going
there but when you get to the larger
sizes you get to
interesting discussions about data
stores and
i've talked about elasticsearch already
it's a famous product for
keeping centralized logging but also the
another component of the cloud native
computing foundation jaeger
it is a tracing product can also uses
elastic search as a data store
so elastic search just writing that down
yeager and elk and jaeger are two ways
to use elasticsearch for traces and
logging and very large systems you know
those kind that use multiple data
centers use apache cassandra
as a large scalable data store for this
stuff i've seen that used for metrics
and i've heard of it being used for
for logging jaeger can also use
cassandra for tracing although i believe
they
prefer you to use elasticsearch because
of elasticsearch does some of the
indexing so they don't have to
and those are just a couple of them
great so
should we i think these will all be this
tight but should
these be push based or pull based or
or am i thinking about monitoring you're
thinking about monitoring and that is a
great question thank you for asking it
looking at it from the metrics point of
view push-based monitoring and
pull-based monitoring is for
pull based is you have a central system
that just pulls a bunch of things and
asks
give me your status give me your status
give me your status on a schedule push
based is
is when the system that produces the
whatever
tells a central thing i did a thing i
did a thing i did a thing
there are two different ways to get at
the same kind of data but they give you
different
shapes of data for things like system
monitoring i mentioned before about
network switches and their performance
that's
almost always done via poll based
monitoring like once every minute two
minutes or however long your interval is
it pulls everything to see how much work
it's done and it reports it in a
centralized database
and you see that far more in like
infrastructure monitoring like
network hardware servers themselves the
server hardware power units
stuff like that you see that as pool
based monitoring most of the time
and why do you think that is because a
lot of these things
don't have an ability to push or if they
do it's through snmp
which is kind of icky to use outside of
networking so it's a lot easier to use
something like
collect d or telegraph to to be able to
do the pulling
just give us some ideas here of what a
telemetry payload should look
like in these types of small situations
yeah payload especially for the small
situations it's whatever the sdk is
building which is almost always json
quite frankly but when you get again to
the medium and larger sizes when you're
doing some centralization it really does
depend on your specific organization
json serializes very fast we spent the
last decade making that extremely
fast everywhere we can get a hold of it
so json's fast
but i'm also seeing some more usage of
protobufs
protocol buffers for some of this stuff
vertical buffers are a bit controversial
because they are very static format
that's not what they're supposed to be
used for yeah vertical buffers are
supposed to be for static formats with
this rigid schema
so you can't really encode a variable
array of
fields onto something with a protocol
buffer but for example look if you're
doing
a metrics format that has
three labels and a value if you know
that's the format you can actually use
protobufs for that but
i'm seeing more and more protobufs in
there perhaps as a carrier format for
something inside
perhaps they need to integrate with the
grpc system for example
yeah robert our show's editor did a
show on drpc and they talked about the
benefits of pro buff
because you can version some of the
fields so maybe that's why people are
reaching
for that and at this scale so the web
app
using a software as a service
centralized place
what size is that payload what does it
normally look like
in volume data volume it's typically
very small
and again for the sas type provider is
it's going to be a json document and
unless you're encoding a ton of stuff
it's going to be probably less than a
couple of kilobytes
and that'll be something they're trying
to push to keep it you know not too
massive
yeah you keep it small to keep the
parsing buffers
you know keep the job of the parser on
the other side to keep that job easy
just kind of increase your event
throughput as a rule of thumb
how fast should this data ship is that
again down to the sdk
it's a lot of down to the sdk but again
you do want to ship it as fast as
possible
most sdks language support permitting do
try to do an asynchronous send on the
background to avoid blocking the
production threads
not every language supports that though
yeah i was reading into
not quite telemetry but google analytics
on some of the mobile apps
you have to specifically enable
developer mode so you can get stuff in
real time but
outside that in production it will batch
it up and send it so once an hour or
something but
yeah mobile's the one case where you
still have a lot of batch mode because
you can't trust the network
and you can't have continuous real-time
monitoring because that's bad on battery
device so you have to build your stuff
to be able to batch it out and
importantly you need to be able to
accept out of order arrival for
telemetry coming from places because you
can get stuff that can be hours old
coming in right now
what sort of data volumes are we talking
about at this level
data volumes are very different
frankly like for a small web application
you're probably looking at somewhere
between
i think of it as events per second
you're probably maybe
less than a thousand events per second
for like a small application like i've i
i've
personally seen systems up to 35 000
events a second that i've managed and
i've heard of
them getting over a million events a
second for truly large
systems wow so at this level
when you're looking at the different sas
price plans
i guess you have to do some sums and say
right if
the sdk says that the packet is 1k
which is big for json i suppose how
quickly does that ship and then you know
how much history do i want and just
multiply that
by seven days or whatever it is yeah is
that a good way to think of that yeah
the sas provider plans a whole lot of
spreadsheeting work i'm afraid yeah just
fake it and knowing how your application
performs yeah and then keep a credit
card on file with a big
balance mm-hmm unfortunately that seems
to be how the small very
small space works yeah and in the real
world
so start a business any type of business
what's a good rule of thumb for how long
the data should be
kept or is that sector specific again a
little bit of
sector specific but for generally what i
have observed is that centralized
logging data which is mostly
strings based which requires expensive
database and tends to be your biggest
data store
you rarely see that preserved more than
about 30 to 60 days just because
it's expensive you know metrics data can
go back 10 years frankly
it may be highly summarized by the time
it gets descend 10 years but you can see
you can keep it that long economically
it's way easier to do
yeah for traces they have the kind of
the centralized logging problem there's
a
high cardinality for that kind of data
which really puts down
downward pressure on your retention
policy so like the software the service
providers
will give you 30 60 days and if you want
more you can negotiate it but it's going
to be money
what makes this data storage expensive
the
the complicated string based data
yeah the it comes down to cardinality
again i'm going to use elasticsearch for
this just because it's famous for the
elk stack
and what makes that expensive is because
of how much analysis elasticsearch does
every time it ingests a new document
because so if you have
a logging statement that just said setup
account 895 in team 42
very natural language stuff what lasik
search does with that
english language string is it runs an
analyzers on there to figure out where
the words are
it tokenizes them so you can actually
create
the terms account number created
in team number and so you can
in your search in search interface
put in created team number and get
all of the count creation events just
because elasticsearch is doing all the
string processing for you
now to do that string processing it has
to do a lot of back end
indexing and storage quite frankly so
it's complex
and keeps all those terms around gets
very large
and very large ends up being very
expensive to keep around
and that's why you see that problem
now contrast this with numbers where you
have you wouldn't see
the account creighton team whatever
there you'd see a created account
account creation counter so it'd
increment a counter
in a given microsecond and you'd have a
couple of tags saying
what type of account it was and which
data center
so you've got little tiny bits of data
you've got two tags and and a one
and that's really tiny it increments the
counter that's already in the database
and you're all good you know it's really
really
tiny so it makes it very cheap to store
i guess that problem gets harder the
bigger you
you get as a company very much so thank
you i'm going to move us on to the final
section of the show
we're going to discuss telemetry data in
the resource-constrained
personal environment so different from
your blog standard web app but obviously
it's got its own challenges
what should we care about in low power
or
poor bandwidth environments so let's
take an application on your
smartphone for those environments you're
looking at
this is a different approach to
telemetry it's simple because you're
dealing with
you don't have the real time assumption
you would in a data center so you need
you want to track as little as possible
because
you're working with mobile providers and
as apple has proven
their threshold for it counts as private
information and what's not private
information changes
and if you suddenly find your telemetry
streams blocked behind a new privacy
control
your engineering org is in a lot of
trouble so you want to be able to
anonymize as much as possible
and do as little as possible like the
very minimum i've seen
is like crash reporting because you need
to know what crashes are and what
systems are
so you can batch upload your crashes in
the background i think that's the
minimum
but actually usage metrics you're
looking at
again trying to keep as little as you
can get away with as possible you're not
trying to maximize the throughput you're
trying to minimize it because every time
that thread is active you're burning
battery
and every time that thread is active in
the foreground you're burning data too
if you're reporting so you want to
minimize it
so could you use the tracing style of
telemetry on this where you could flick
a feature toggle and get some
proper data or or do you just have to
not think about that at all
application tracing is its own thing
because again you have that because
tracing is also a very fairly high
volume technique when you look at for
things like
a data center because you're getting a
lot of discrete events out of that
anytime you enter exit a function you're
potentially creating an event that'll
have to be reported home
and again that's the kind of thing that
can get costly in terms of battery
and phone home and might get
banned in the future of future privacy
controls so you have to take a
kind of a different approach to it you
definitely have your developer builds do
that
you can do that stuff that gets side
loaded and tested and different things
when you're qualifying your hardware you
can use that to try to figure out how
things work
but again in those resource constrained
environments the overhead of having the
tracer in place
is that heisenberg uncertainty principle
problem by observing the system you
change the system so you
mostly get an idea as to how it's
usually supposed to run but that's with
the tracer turned on
yeah you could miss skip a part of your
program or something like that
i guess if you're doing some customers
some support you could get them to go to
the
settings and debug section and switch
something on for you just as and when
i've seen that model used a few times
yeah because a lot of apps will
the support will ask you to switch
something on and then send the log files
to the email
system on your phone which is obviously
a bit slower but
it's still a form of telemetry isn't it
it is and it's a kind of opt-in
telemetry because the user has to take
active action which is much easier to
defend
when it comes time to google or apple
saying this is not private information
you can't have it
yeah my next question i think you've
touched on already
in a mobile environment on a modern
smartphone
what is useful data from an app
i think you've already said the crash
data
crash data is the absolute minimum
because that tells you
your compatibility with different
hardware models this is especially
important to the android space
but yeah it's the crash data is absolute
minimum and you typically have a
different stream for telemetry for crash
report data that need to sail like
application telemetry simply
because the different functions you know
you've got a crash report
there's actual apis in the in the os i
believe for some of that stuff
that you can hook into so you report it
differently but
for application level data again it's
like how little can you get away with
and how different is is this from
collecting logs
in the back end servers of the app it's
a it's a very different thing because
when you're collecting logs in the back
end servers of the app you can actually
assume always on networking and it's
relatively high speed which is a
different architecture completely
so you can have a process like elastics
file beat sitting on your server that
just sort of
watching each file waiting for a new
line to show up that'll pick up and zach
even zoom it off to wherever it's going
next
whereas with a with a mobile with a
smartphone
you may have a thread whose job it is is
to see if we've had any batch
batch events that we need to send
upstream and then once the thread goes
active
in the foreground and can talk to
network it burps it off
in your experience are these things that
something should be always on or
something a user has to enable
or support can remotely activate i guess
that comes down to the app store
potentially it comes down to the app
stores policy i'm afraid i mean
certain amount of user tracking is
already done through the app for the
advertising model for
both stores but you're walking a kind of
a
thin line between are you
trying to pretend are you looking like
advertising where you need to track
every single thing a user does for
revenue purposes
or are you trying to back it off a
little bit and
try to stay below the bar that the
advertise that the app stores are
looking for these sorts of phone home
applications your regular application
function is probably one of the better
ways because when you
click on a something and it phones home
you can still get
those backend traces for what happened
and what the user session was that's
still there
yeah because i guess you've got to try
and think about what data do i need to
give a good experience so it's still on
the app store versus
do i need to know if the user is using
that feature
this is where feature flags come in a
lot of ways phoning home for feature
flags is
a way to do that and it's a
bit like dealing with a javascript
application in browsers
in the way that you only have some
control over what's going on in there
and how can we add telemetry without
decreasing
the readability of code or affecting
performance
that's really up to the sdks in a lot of
ways especially if you're using a third
party now if you're building an in-house
sdk
say like you're a medium a large size
company who's building your own internal
system for these sorts of things
that is something the sdk designers
really need to pay attention to
is developer usability the tracing
systems that i
looked at are pretty good about that
because like when you you have a one
line of code you need to insert to say i
want to start tracing here
and another line to say stop tracing and
at that point magic happens
and that makes it very easy for the
developer in that case
what should not be captured and shipped
would you say
that would be what i consider toxic data
that's
that is the financial data privacy data
health data
and security data quite frankly you
really don't want to be passing around
pii
european gdpr changed the world in a lot
of ways for what counts as private data
email address that thing that was
counted as a username for
across the entire web for the last 15
years is now considered
pii under gdpr so if you're logging
the username of logins you're now
logging pii which means
you need to treat that the same way you
do pii in your regular application which
is usually
more restrictive than a good telemetry
system needs so you need to be very
careful to keep that sort of toxic data
the stuff that requires special handling
and has penalties attached if you get it
wrong
out of your telemetry systems and pii
is personal identifiable information
yep yeah you need to know who the user
is
so you can do your job so if you need to
log the email and that's the primary way
to log in then
you just have to justify i think on your
gdpr
policy it can and a safer way is to
disambiguate that from the
email address into whatever it is that's
showing up in your database which may be
an integer of some kind
so instead of logging the email that was
on the form log the account id in your
database
which is disambiguated from things and
it's probably what you'll be looking up
in the database anyway if you have to go
look in there
yeah it's something you can still link
to somebody
a customer but if it gets out it's not
going to do any harm
yeah and like an email address which is
generally of
identifiable now yeah could we talk a
little bit about software telemetry
and how that's done in the hello sign
mobile app is that something you're
familiar with or
no not really yeah the mobile
development i'm pretty far from so like
honestly i'm not sure how that's done i
do know the
front end for our regular web
application stuff okay
take us through if you if you're allowed
a little bit of that
it's probably no secret that i've got an
elk stack running internally and
that's that's primarily what we're using
for our
for our centralized logging it's been
going very well for a bunch of years now
we also have a metric stack based on
influx db and grafana which is
again working very well we had some
teething issues early with
understanding how statsd worked for
metric summarization but i figured out
the bugs in that particular problem and
came up with a better way to handle it
so it's been a good run
good run frankly the telemetry systems
we've got right now are
kind of my baby so it's been fun to
watch them grow up
i like it i think that's uh near the end
of the show now
one of my favorite questions what is the
future do you predict
for telemetry oh is it still going to be
called telemetry or are we going to come
up with another name
i have a feeling that because the
pillars of observability or have a lot
of mind share right now we're going to
start seeing a lot more
observability stuff building observable
systems is a concept you're starting to
see
in books and blog posts right now i
think that's going to increase
especially as the open telemetry project
finally releases
and you start seeing the kubernetes side
of the world start
going all in on these systems you're
going to see more
rebranding of software telemetry as more
of an observability thing but i think
telemetry as a word was going to stay
with us
and obviously software telemetry is
extremely important for software
engineers
and companies but if there was one thing
you'd like a software engineer to
remember from our show
what would that be the one thing to keep
in mind
is to pay attention to your data safety
the toxic data that i spoke about
earlier
if your application is handling
financial privacy or health information
your telemetry systems can possibly
can possibly contain that so you need to
make sure that your telemetry systems
are
clean of that and if they're not clean
to that you need to make sure that you
have ways to clean up the spills
because when you mishandle this
information your company faces a lot of
liabilities
so state of privacy and health
information is changing every year
so keep up with the changes and don't be
afraid to rewrite your telemetry history
if it turns out you're logging things
it's really shouldn't have been doing
i think i've seen some tools that you
can point out your github
repositories or any git source code and
it'll look for those types of things do
you know of any that will
go and look through your logs and try
and flag up that so you can you know
before you get into production
uh i don't know any off the top of my
head i do know of a few
checkers that will check the logs stream
themselves for pii
amazon macy is one microsoft has a
downloadable one that you can run on
your own
and i believe azure also has an endpoint
where you can submit stuff and it'll
flag pii that it finds in there
then not seeing honestly i'm not seeing
a whole lot for just download and run
because
these major systems tend to be built on
machine learning models
which are they're not releasing i'm
afraid so this there's not a lot in the
open source space that will give you
these sorts of detectors hopefully in
the future we'll fix that
yeah i think the one i'm thinking of
looks for secrets
yes in your environment stuff that's key
but we're looking at things like
passing password hashes in your logs i
mean that's the kind of thing that i'm
looking for that i'm kind of warning
against
before we finish up was there anything
we missed that you would have liked me
to ask or
you'd like to mention there is one and
it's a little bit of
promotional but there's something a lot
of engineers don't quite
realize is that their telemetry systems
are still considered a business record
and business records are subpoenaable
so for example if your company got
caught with its
pants around its ankle for gdpr in a big
enough way
the regulators can and will ask for your
telemetry systems
ask for telemetry data so it's a good
idea
when you're thinking about making
changes to telemetry systems to consider
how would we respond if the regulator
says
we need you to keep all our not the
regulator if your own legal department
says
we need to keep all of this data for
until we say otherwise
just in case someone decides to sue us
about this particular thing
and having a plan in place to respond to
that will take a whole lot of the panic
out of that moment yeah i suppose you
could just say right we'll keep it
forever
you can try it's all cost in the end
and the thing is that these databases
change formats
elasticsearch is famous every time it
makes a major version
change it only restores the like the
previous versions of elasticsearch
data so if you have backups going back
seven years and a new version comes out
you have to reprocess six years of
history to be able to make sure it's
still restorable
and that's a hard process that's the
age-old problem of
what media to keep backups on isn't it
oh yes archive
digital information oh yeah and the data
format shift too
and that's prob that's where i see the
biggest digital rot these days because
these days you just throw it on an s3
bucket no one cares except for whoever's
paying the bill
but being able to restore it's another
problem so where can people
find out more they can follow you on
twitter but how else could they get in
touch
uh the twitter is the probably the best
way to get a hold of me these days and
that's where i keep my
primary social media presence these days
i'm
speaking here and there getting the book
out took a lot of my time away as
did this pandemic we're in the middle of
so hopefully to get out back on the
speaking circuit a bit more
catch me at some place you typically
will find me at like the lisa conference
i'm trying to get to an sre conference
and some of the devops days around the
area i've been
known to speak that's the large
infrastructure
what does lisa stand for again large
infrastructure systems administration
although they sort of dropped the
acronym a few years ago
that's right well jamie thank you for
coming on the show it's been a real
pleasure this is gavin
henry for software engineering radio
thank you for listening
keeping your teams on top of the latest
tech developments is a monumental
challenge
helping them get answers to urgent
problems they face daily is even harder
that's why 66 of all fortune 100
companies
count on o'reilly online learning at
o'reilly your teams will get live
courses
tons of resources interactive scenarios
and sandboxes
and fast answers to their pressing
questions see what o'reilly online
learning can do for your teams
visit o'reilly.com for a demo
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com you can also email us
at team
sc-radio.net this and all other episodes
of sc radio is licensed under creative
commons license 2.5
thanks for listening